David Swensen, who remember I said he was
the inventor of the swap, which is a real
claim to fame because swaps
total in the hundreds of trillions.
It's amazing.
I thought this was going to be a polite introduction.
I used to be proud of the
swap thing, but that was before the crisis.
Well, that's financial innovation.
I think swaps are very important new technology.
We've been talking about that.
So anyway, just to remind you, David Swensen
came to Yale in 1985 when the portfolio was
worth less than a billion, less than one billion.
And as of June 2010, it's 16.7 billion.
And climbing.
Okay.
And this is a financial crisis.
But between 2009 and 2010...
The portfolio went up 1.4 billion.
So there's no crisis around here.
Well, there was a little hitch at
one point, but that kind of thing happens.
And David Swensen also...
I take pride in training young people in finance.
David Swensen has done the same with many young people.
Notably, Andrew Golden, who heads the
Princeton portfolio, is one of your trainees.
Thank you.
And he's had a similarly,
almost as spectacular record as well.
Well, with that introduction, I will
turn it over to David Swensen.
Thank you.
So I've been at Yale for,
I guess, more than 25 years now.
And for most of the 25 years, if
there was any publicity, the publicity was pretty good.
For the past couple of years,
it's been a little bit mixed.
And I liked it better before the publicity was mixed.
I liked it when every article that you
would read had something great to say about the
Yale approach or the Swensen model.
But after the collapse of Lehman Brothers
and the onset of the financial crisis, it
didn't take very long for the negative headlines to appear.
As a matter of fact, I carry around
this Barron's article that appeared in November 2008.
And the title was Crash Course.
And it talked about colleges cutting
budgets, freezing hiring, scaling back building projects.
And it blamed the Yale model and
the Swensen approach for being too aggressive.
They said in Barron's that, University of New York.
The endowment should own more
stocks and bonds, less in alternatives.
Because the alternatives provided too
little diversification and too little liquidity.
So I thought what we could do today as a
jumping-off point is talk about what it is that Barron's
meant when they were talking about
the Swensen approach or the Yale model.
And I think when it was
successful it was the Yale model.
And when it failed, it was the
Swensen approach, which I really don't like.
There's an asymmetry.
I think it's a big problem.
But I think we need to do more.
If you're interested, go to the site.
I have a job.
I'm a lawyer.
I work for the American Academy of Law.
So I'm a lawyer.
I work in law.
I work for the American Academy of Law.
symmetry there. I keep thinking that I should
name it after one of the guys in
the office and maybe it should
be the Takahashi approach instead of the
Swenson approach. It's time for him to
have some glory, right? Talk about what it
is that Barron's meant by the Swenson approach
or the or the Yale model and see
whether indeed the criticisms that
they levy that there's too little
diversification and too little liquidity
whether those criticisms are valid.
But to do that let's go back to 1985 when
I first arrived at Yale. It was April 1st, 1985
for those of you who care about April
Fool's Day. I came from a six-year stint
on Wall Street and I had
no significant portfolio management experience. As Bob
mentioned in the beginning of the book, I
was a student at the University of New York.
I was a student at the University of New York.
In his introduction, I'd been
involved with structuring the first swap
transaction in 1981 when I when I
worked for Salomon Brothers. It was a swap
between IBM and the World Bank and later
Lehman Brothers hired me to set up their
swap operations. And so generally what I
was doing on Wall Street was working
with new financial technologies and being
involved with the early days of
swaps transactions.
It was a much smaller market then. It
wasn't hundreds of trillions. And it was a
much less efficient market then.
So the trades were incredibly profitable.
Commodity swaps today trade on razor-thin
margins and tend not to be
anywhere near as profitable as they
were when the markets were much less
efficient. How did I end up at Yale? Well, one of my
dissertation advisors called me and said they needed somebody to help me.
to manage the portfolio. And after coming
to New Haven and talking to him
about the the job, I realized that my
heart wasn't in Wall Street. My heart was
in the world of education and at Yale
in particular. So I came up here amazed that
I was responsible as chief investment
officer for this portfolio that was less
than a billion but close to a billion.
And the first thing I did was I was
I looked around to see what other
people were doing. That seemed like a sensible
way to approach the portfolio management
problem. There must be some smart people
at Harvard or Princeton or
Stanford putting together portfolios that that
make sense for endowed institutions. What
I saw was that colleges and
universities had on average fifty percent
of their portfolio in US stocks
and
forty percent of their portfolio in US
bonds and cash and ten percent in a
smattering of alternatives. Even though
I had no direct portfolio management
experience, I had studied at Yale and
Jim Tobin and Bill Brainerd were my
dissertation advisors and I understood some
of the the basic principles of
corporate finance. And one of the first things that
you learn when you study finance theory
is that diversification is a great thing.
Jim Tobin won the Nobel Prize in part
for his work related to the subject of
diversification. In fact when a New York
Times reporter asked Jim to explain in
layman's terms what it was that he won
the Nobel Prize for, Jim said, well I
guess you could say don't put
all your eggs in one basket.
I didn't know you got a
Nobel Prize for that but that's...
We told our students that
that phrase goes back to 1802.
Okay, so if it goes back to 1802, Jim was just picking
up on the vernacular and used it as a way to describe
what it is that he did his work
for. And Harry Markowitz, who actually did a fair
amount of his work on modern
portfolio theory at Yale's Coles Foundation,
said,
has said that diversification is a free lunch.
Right, I mean didn't you
learn in introductory economics and intermediate
that there ain't no such thing as
a free lunch, that economists are always talking
about trade-offs, if you want more
of this you have less of that.
Well, with diversification that's not true.
Right, if you diversify your portfolio for
a given level of return, you can
generate that return at lower risk. If
you diversify for a given level of risk,
you can generate higher returns.
So diversification is this great thing.
It's a free lunch. It's
something that everybody should embrace.
Well, if you look at the portfolios that I
saw in the world of endowment investing in the mid-1980s,
they weren't diversified. Right, if you've got half
of your assets in a single asset class,
U.S. stocks, and you have 90%
of your assets in U.S. marketable securities,
you're not diversified. Half of your assets in
a single asset class is way too much.
And the 90% that are in stocks and
bonds, under many circumstances, will respond to the same
driver of returns, interest rates, in the same way. Right?
Lower interest rates, mathematically, are good
for bonds, and lower interest rates
lower the discount rate that you use to do that.
And the discount future earnings stream, so they're
probably going to be good for stocks, too.
And vice versa.
And the second thing I thought about was
the notion that endowments have a longer time horizon
than any investor that I know.
And if you've got a long time horizon,
you should be rewarded by accepting equity risks,
because those equity risks, even
though they might not reward you
in the short run, will
reward you in the long run.
So with a mission as a manager of an
endowment to preserve the purchasing power of the portfolio
in perpetuity, I expected that other
endowments would have substantial equity exposures
to take advantage of the fact that in the long
run, that's where you're going to generate the greatest returns.
But if you think about those endowment
allocations that I saw in the mid-1980s,
40% of the assets were in bonds
and cash, which are low expected return assets.
So the portfolios that I saw when I got
to Yale failed the basic common sense tests of diversification
and equity orientation.
And it prompted
me and my colleagues to go down a different path
to put together a portfolio
that had reasonable exposure to equities
and put together a portfolio that was sensibly diversified.
So I'd like to talk about how it is
that we got from where we were in the mid-1980s
to where we ended up in the early to mid-1990s.
And where we remain today.
And to do that, I'd like to put it in the context
of the basic tools that we have available to us as investors.
And these tools are the tools that you can
employ if you're managing your portfolio as an individual.
The tools that I have to employ when
I'm managing Yale's portfolio as an institutional investor.
And they're basically three things that
you can do to affect your returns.
First of all, you can decide what
assets you're going to have in the portfolio
and in which proportions you'll hold those assets.
So that's the asset allocation decision.
How much in domestic stocks, how much
in foreign stocks, how much in real estate.
If you're an institutional investor, how much
in timber, how much in leverage buyouts,
how much in venture capital.
Fundamental decision of the asset allocation decision.
Of how it is that the portfolio assets are allocated.
The second thing that you can
do is make a market timing decision.
So if you've established targets for your portfolio.
Targets with respect to how much in domestic stocks,
how much in domestic bonds, how much in foreign stocks.
And then, because in the short run, you think that,
let's say domestic stocks are expensive and foreign stocks are cheap.
You decide to hold more foreign
stocks and less in domestic stocks.
That bet, that short term bet against your
long term targets is a market timing decision.
And the returns that are attributable to
that deviation from your long term targets
are the returns that would be attributable to market timing.
And the third source of returns
has to do with security selection.
So,
you've got your allocation to domestic equities.
If you buy the market, and the way that you
buy the market is to buy an index fund that
holds all of the securities in the market
in the proportions that they exist in the market.
If you buy the market, then
your returns to security selection are zero.
Because your portfolio is going to
perform in line with the market.
But if you make security selection bets,
if you
decide that you want to try and beat the market,
then
that bet, or that series of bets,
will define your returns attributable to security selection.
So, if you decide
that you think the prospects of Ford
are superior to the prospects of GM,
well, you want to overweight Ford
and underweight GM.
And if that turns out to be
a good bet,
and you're rewarded,
because Ford outperforms and GM underperforms,
then you have a positive return to security selection.
If the converse is true,
then you have a negative return to security selection.
But one of the really
important facts about security selection
is that
if you play for free, it's a zero-sum game.
Because if you've overweighted Ford and underweighted GM,
there has to be
some other investor, or group of investors,
that are underweight Ford and overweight GM.
Because this is all relative to the market.
And so,
if you're overweight Ford and underweight GM,
and somebody else is
underweight Ford and overweight GM,
well, at the end of
the day, the amount by which
the winner wins equals the
amount by which the loser loses.
And so it's a zero-sum game.
But of course, if you take into account
the fact that it costs money to play the game,
it turns into a negative-sum game.
And the negative sum is the amount that's
siphoned off by Wall Street.
And Wall Street takes its pound of flesh
in the form of market impact,
in the form of commissions,
in the form of fees
that are charged
to manage the portfolio actively.
And then sometimes there are even fees
to consultants to choose the managers.
So there's an enormous drain from the system
that causes the active investment activity
to be a negative-sum game.
And so the question is,
what's the best way to manage the financial impact
for those investors that decide to play?
So let's take these in turn
and start out with asset allocation.
So asset allocation is far and away
the most important tool
that we have available to us as investors.
And when I first started thinking about this
25 years ago,
I had a very technical law that says
that asset allocation is the most important tool
because it seemed pretty obvious
that that was going to be the most powerful determinant
of returns.
But it turns out that it's not really
a law of finance
that asset allocation dominates returns.
It's a behavioral result
of how it is that we as individual investors
or we as institutional investors
manage our portfolios.
So if I make it back to my office,
traversing these icy sidewalks,
I could go back,
I could take Yale's $17 or $18 billion
and put it all in Google stock.
Now if I did that,
I'm not sure how long I'd keep my job,
it might be fun for a while,
but that would probably be damaging
to my employment prospects.
But if I did that,
asset allocation would have almost nothing to say
about Yale's returns.
It would be the idiosyncratic return
associated with Google
that would determine whether the endowment
went up or down or stayed flat.
And so security selection
would be the overwhelming
important determinant
of returns for Yale's endowment.
And if it wasn't exciting enough
to sell everything
and put it all in Google stock,
maybe I could go back to my office
and start day trading bond futures.
Well, if I took Yale's entire $17 or $18 billion
and started trading bond futures with it,
asset allocation would have very little to say
about Yale's returns.
Security selection would probably have very little
to say about Yale's returns.
It would all be about
market timing ability.
And if I'm great at following the trend,
the trend is your friend,
of course that's true until it's not.
Or if I've got some sort of marvelous scheme
to outsmart all the other smart people
who are trading in the bond market,
that could generate some nice returns,
but those returns would have nothing to do
with asset allocation,
nothing to do with security selection,
everything to do with market timing.
Of course, these sound like ridiculous things, right?
I mean, everybody in this room knows
that I'm not going to go back
and put Yale's entire endowment in one stock.
And they also know that
I'm not going to go back
and day trade futures with the endowment.
I'm going to go back
and the portfolio's going to look
a lot like it looked yesterday and the day before
and the month before.
And the year before that and the year before that.
Because as investors,
whether we're individual investors
or institutional investors,
we tend to have a sensible, stable approach
to asset allocation.
And within the asset allocation framework that we employ,
we tend to hold well-diversified portfolios of securities
within each of the asset classes.
So that means that asset allocation
is going to be the predominant determinant of returns.
You know, Bob Shiller and I have a colleague
at the School of Management, Roger Ibbotson,
who's done a fair amount of work
looking at the various sources of returns for investors.
And a number of years ago,
he came out with a finding that more than 90%
of the variability of returns
in institutional portfolios
had to do with the asset allocation decision.
And that was a very widely read
and widely accepted conclusion.
In that same study,
I thought that there was a more interesting conclusion,
and that was that asset allocation actually determined
more than 100% of investor returns.
Now, how could that be?
How could asset allocation determine
more than 100% of returns?
Well, it goes back to the discussion that we had
about security selection
and the fact that it's
not free to play the game.
And the same thing is true of market timing.
If somebody is over-weighting a particular asset class
relative to the long-term targets that they've got,
well, there's got to be
an offsetting position in the markets.
Market timing is expensive in the same way
that security selection is expensive.
And so it too is a zero-sum game,
even though the analysis that you'd apply to market timing
isn't quite as clear and
crisp as in the closed system
that you've got with any individual securities market.
So if security selection and market timing
are negative-sum games,
then asset allocation would explain
more than 100% of the returns.
And on average, for the community as a whole,
because investors do engage in market timing,
investors do engage in security selection,
those are going to be negative-sum games,
and you have to subtract the leakages
occurring because of security selection and market timing
in order to get down to
the returns that you would get
if you just took your asset allocation targets
and implemented them passively.
So it turns out that asset allocation
is the most important way that we express
our basic tenets of investment philosophy.
I talked about the importance of having an equity bias.
Well, these are some of Roger Ibbotson's data.
He's got this publication called
Stocks, Bonds, Bills, and Inflation,
although I think he might have sold it to Morningstar,
so maybe it's Morningstar's publication now.
And it actually is an outgrowth of some academic research
that he did decades ago.
And the basic drill was, starting in 1925,
looking at a number of asset classes,
the ones that I've got here are
treasury bills, treasury bonds,
large stocks, small stocks,
and then as a benchmark, inflation.
Starting the investment at the end of 1925,
taking whatever income was generated from that investment,
reinvesting it, and seeing where you end up
at the end of the period.
And what I've got here are the numbers from 1925
to 2009.
And if you did that with treasury bills,
which are short-term loans to the U.S. government,
one of the least risky assets imaginable,
you would have ended up with 21 times your money
over the period.
Think about that, 21 times your money,
that's pretty good.
But if you think about the fact that inflation
consumed a multiple of 12,
well, you didn't end up with a lot after inflation.
And if you're an institution like Yale,
and you only want to consume after inflation returns,
so you can maintain the purchasing power of the portfolio,
well, 21 times, but taking off 12 times for inflation,
eh, not so good.
One of the interesting things
about the stocks, bonds, bills,
and inflation numbers over long periods
is that they correspond to our sense of the relationship
between the riskiness of the asset
and the notion that if you accept more risk,
you should get higher returns.
And so if you move out the risk spectrum,
and instead of looking at treasury bills,
you look at treasury bonds,
you end up with a multiple of 86 times.
That's pretty good, 86 times.
I mean, it's a lot better
than, whatever, 21 times for bills.
But it's still not a huge return
for decades and decades of investing.
So what happens if you move away from lending money,
in this case, lending money to the government,
to owning equities?
The multiple over this period,
and this includes the crash in 1929,
the market collapse in 1987,
and the most recent financial crisis,
in spite of those blips,
you would have ended up with 2,592 times your money.
That's stunning.
Like, way more than 86 times
and way more than 21 times.
So over long periods of time,
you do end up being rewarded for accepting equity risk.
And what would have happened
if you would have put the money in small stocks
and let her run?
12,226 times your money.
So the conclusion is pretty obvious.
This notion that if you've got a long time horizon,
you want to expose your portfolio to equities
makes an enormous amount of sense.
As a matter of fact,
the first time I took a look at these numbers
was back in 1986
when I was teaching,
probably a predecessor to the
class that Bob Shiller's teaching,
it was a lecture class in finance,
and I was preparing the
lecture that had to do with
long-term,
investment philosophy.
And that's when I first saw these numbers
and I was a little bit disconcerted
when I put them together because I thought,
gee,
21 times for bills,
86 times for bonds,
12,226 times for small stocks,
maybe the right thing to do is to just
put the whole portfolio into small stocks
and forget about it.
And my first problem was,
if that were true,
what was I going to say
for the next 10 weeks of lectures?
My longer-term problem was
if the investment committee figured out
that all we needed to
do was put the whole portfolio
in small stocks and that that
was the way to investment success,
I wouldn't have a job.
They wouldn't need me to do that.
And I had a wife and young children
and I like getting a paycheck
and being able to feed and house them.
So I took a look at the data more carefully
and there are a number of examples
of what it is that I'm going to talk about,
but the most profound example
remains around the great crash in 1929.
And if you'd had your whole portfolio
in small stocks at the peak,
by the end of 1929,
you would have lost 54% of your money.
By the end of 1930,
you would have lost 38% of your money.
Another 38%, that is.
By the end of 1931,
you would have lost another 50%.
And by June of 1932, for good measure,
you would have lost another 32%.
So for every dollar that you had at the peak,
at the trough,
you would have had 10 cents left.
And it doesn't matter whether you're an investor
with the strongest stomach known to mankind
or you're an institutional investor
with the longest investment horizon imaginable,
at some point,
when the dollars are turning into dimes,
they're going to say,
this is a completely ridiculous thing
to accept this much risk in the portfolio.
I can't stand it.
I'm selling all my small stocks
and going to buy treasury bonds or treasury bills, right?
And that's exactly what people did.
And there was this sense
in the 1930s, 1940s,
even into the 50s and 60s,
that heavy equity exposures
weren't a responsible thing for a fiduciary.
When I was writing my book,
I was kind of fooling around,
looking at articles from the Saturday Evening Post.
And I know everybody here is too young
to have seen the Saturday Evening Post
when it was still publishing.
But you've all seen Norman Rockwell prints, right?
Well, he was famous for doing covers
for the Saturday Evening Post.
And there was this article in the 1930s,
that's actually before my time,
so I was looking at things in the library,
not things that actually had been delivered to my doorstep.
And the commentator said
that it was ridiculous
that stocks were called securities,
that they were so risky
that we should call stocks insecurities.
There was just this visceral dislike
for the risks that were associated
with the stock market
because it had caused so many investors so much pain.
So yes, stocks are a great thing
for investors with long time horizons,
but you need to diversify
because you've got to be able
to live through
those inevitable periods
where risky assets produce results
that are sometimes so bad as to be frightening.
Second source of return, market timing.
A few years ago,
a group of former colleagues of mine
gave me a party at the Yale Club
and they presented me with a copy
of Keynes' General Theory.
Because back when I used to teach
a big finance class like this,
the last class always involved
reading from Keynes.
And I think Keynes was one of the best authors
about investing in financial markets,
bar none.
I remember one of my students telling me afterwards
that I was reading from Keynes
as if I were reading from the Bible.
And I had this paperback copy
that was falling apart.
And my former students remembered this
and they gave me this beautiful
first edition of Keynes.
And I was on the train back from New York
where the party had occurred to New Haven.
And I found this quote.
The idea of wholesale shifts
is for various reasons impracticable
and indeed undesirable.
Most of those who attempt to
sell too late and buy too late
and do both too often increase their risk.
And heavy expenses,
there's that negative sum game thing,
and developing too unsettled
and speculative a state of mind.
And as in most things,
the data support Keynes' conclusions.
Morningstar did a study
of all of the mutual funds
in the U.S. domestic equity market.
And there were 17 categories of funds.
And what they did with this study
is they looked at 10 years of returns
and compared dollar-weighted returns
to time-weighted returns.
Now time-weighted returns are simply
the returns that are generated year in and year out.
If you get an offering memorandum or a prospectus,
they'll show you the time-weighted return.
If you look at the advertisements
where Fidelity's touting its latest, greatest funds,
the returns that you see are time-weighted returns.
Dollar-weighted returns take into account cash flows.
All right, so in a dollar-weighted return,
if investors put more money into the fund
in a particular year,
that year's return will have a greater weight
in the calculation.
So here we have all
the mutual funds in the U.S.,
17 categories, time-weighted versus dollar-weighted.
In every one of those categories,
the dollar-weighted returns
were less than the time-weighted returns.
What does that mean?
That means that investors systematically made
perverse decisions
as to when to invest
and when to disinvest from mutual funds.
What investors were doing,
they were buying in after a fund
had shown strong relative performance
and selling after a fund
had shown poor relative performance.
So they were systematically buying high and selling low.
And it doesn't matter whether you do that
with great enthusiasm and in great volume,
it's a really, really bad way to make money.
Very difficult.
So the conclusion for these individuals
that operate in the mutual fund market is
that their market timing decisions
were systematically perverse.
I also took a look
at the top 10 internet funds
during the tech bubble.
This is something I published in my book
for individual investors.
And if you looked at the top 10 internet funds
three years before and three years after the bubble,
the time-weighted return was 1.5% per year.
If you look at that and you say,
1.5% per year,
well, the market went way up and way down,
but 1.5% per year, that's not so bad.
No harm, no foul.
Investors invested $13.7 billion
and lost $9.5 billion.
So they lost 72% of what they invested.
How could it be that
they lost 72% of the money
that they invested when the time-weighted return
was 1.5% per year for six years?
Well, they weren't invested in the internet funds in 1997,
and they weren't invested in 1998,
and they weren't invested in early 1999.
It was in late 1999 and early 2000
that all the money piled in at the very top.
And then in 2001 and 2002,
bitterly disappointed, they sold.
So they lost 72% of what they put in,
even though the time-weighted returns
were 1.5% per year positive.
So institutions don't get a free pass either.
If you look at the crash in October 1987,
which was an extraordinary event,
I think the capitalists,
I think the calculation I did
put it at a 25 standard deviation event,
which is essentially an impossibility.
But however you measure it,
it was an extraordinary event.
And what happened on October 19, 1987?
Well, stock markets the world around
went down by more than 20%.
What people forget is,
along with the stock markets going down,
there was a huge rally in government bonds,
flight to safety.
So stocks were cheaper,
bonds were more expensive,
and so were the bonds.
What did institutional investors do?
Well, they got scared and they sold stocks
and bought bonds.
Same thing, buying high, selling low.
As a matter of fact,
endowments took six years
to get their post-crash equity allocations
back up to where they were before the crash,
arguably underweighted in equities
and the heart of one of the greatest bull markets
of all time.
So it seems that investors,
whether they're individual or institutional,
have this perverse predilection
to chasing performance,
buying something after it's gone up,
selling something after it's gone down,
and using market timing
to damage portfolio returns.
The final tool that we have available today
to us as investors is security selection.
I cite a study in my book,
Unconventional Success,
conducted by Rob Arnott,
that does a very good job
at looking at 20 years' worth of mutual fund returns,
and he says that there's about a 14% chance
that, or historically,
there was a 14% chance of beating the market
after adjusting for fees and taxes.
So you'd think zero-sum game
would be a coin flip 50-50,
but because of the leakages from the system
and because of taxes,
the probability of winning goes down to 14%.
But oh, by the way,
that 14% ignores two very important things.
One is that a huge percentage of mutual funds
have front-end loads.
If you call your friendly broker
to buy a mutual fund,
they'll extract a payment of 2 or
3 or 4 or 5 or 6%.
Those numbers aren't included,
so if you included the loads,
that would make the likelihood of winning
substantially less than 14%,
but even more important
is the concept of survivorship bias.
If you look at 20 years' worth of returns,
the only returns that you can look at
are the returns of the
funds that survived for 20 years.
Well, which funds didn't survive?
Almost always the funds
that don't survive are the failures.
So you're only looking at the winners.
If you look at the winners
and you only have a 14% chance,
if you take into account the losers,
that 14% chance has to go to essentially zero.
And is survivorship bias an important phenomenon?
It is.
The Center for Research on Securities Prices
has a survivorship bias-free
U.S. mutual fund database,
meaning that it tracks the funds that fail.
There were 30,361 funds in the database.
19,129 were living.
11,232 were dead.
So almost a,
or more than a third of the funds
in this survivorship bias-free database
were ones that had died.
And they died mostly because they failed.
And that's kind of an honorable way to die.
There are other ways to die.
If you're a big mutual fund complex like Fidelity,
and you've got an underperforming fund,
what you tend to do is something like,
well, let's merge that into this fund
that has good performance.
And guess what happens?
Fidelity loses a fund that has bad performance,
and the one that has good performance
has more assets,
and as they merge the underperforming fund into it,
it makes them look like they're
a more successful fund management firm.
There's one other aspect of security selection
that's important.
An aspect other than the fact that
it's a negative sum game,
very tough for practitioners to win.
And that has to do with the degree
of opportunity that you've got in various asset classes.
A number of years ago,
I wanted to come up with a way of identifying,
in an analytical manner,
where it is that we could find
the most attractive investment opportunities.
And as far as I know,
financial economists haven't determined
a way to directly measure
how efficient individual markets are.
So I took a look at distributions of returns
for various asset classes,
and I had this notion
that if a market priced assets efficiently,
the distribution of returns around
the market return would be very tight.
Now why would that be?
Well, if somebody makes a big bet
in an efficient market,
by definition, whether that bet succeeds or fails,
has to do with more luck than sense.
Because the premise is that these assets
are efficiently priced,
and you don't make a
big win on a big bet
unless there's an inefficiency that you're exploiting.
So if you're making big bets
in an efficiently priced market,
you might win one year and gather more assets,
and you might win another year and gather more assets,
but ultimately your luck's going to run out,
and you're going to fail,
and then people will fire you,
and you'll lose your assets,
and lose your income stream.
So the right thing to
do in an efficiently priced market
is to hug the benchmark.
People call it closet indexing.
Look like everybody else,
and, you know, we're human beings.
We don't like firing people.
We don't like admitting we're wrong.
And so if somebody has kind of market-like performance,
and maybe it's not all that outstanding,
say, okay, fine,
we'll just continue with
this particular investment strategy,
even though it's not doing great things,
at least it's not doing terrible things.
On the other end of the spectrum,
maybe there's not even a market
that you can match with your investment strategy.
I mean, think about venture capital.
I mean, how is it
that you could index venture capital?
You can't.
It's a bunch of private partnerships
and a bunch of idiosyncratic enterprises,
and even if you wanted to,
you couldn't match the market.
So you're forced to go out
and forge your own path
and live and die by the decisions that you make.
So how does this kind of thought piece
translate into real numbers?
So again, we're looking at 10 years' worth of returns
for various asset classes.
I look at the difference between the top quartile manager
and the bottom quartile,
the difference between first and third quartile.
You could use any measure of distribution that you want.
And in the bond market,
which is probably the most
efficiently priced of all markets,
and the reason it's most efficiently priced
is because bonds are just math, right?
You've got coupons, you've got principal,
you've got probabilities of default.
It's the most easily analyzed
of all the assets in which we invest.
The difference between top quartile and bottom quartile
is a half a percent per annum, almost nothing.
All bond managers are jammed together
right in the heart of the distribution
because if they were out there making crazy bets
and generating returns that were fundamentally different
from the market,
they'd be in that category of,
yeah, sure, it's great when it works,
but when it doesn't, you're dead.
Large cap stocks,
less efficiently priced than bonds,
but still pretty efficiently priced,
two percentage points per annum difference,
first to third quartile over ten years.
Foreign stocks, less efficiently priced
than those in the domestic markets,
four points per year.
Then you move into the hedge fund world,
the part of the hedge fund world that we call
absolute return at Yale,
7.1 percentage points first to third quartile.
Real estate, much less efficiently priced
than marketable securities,
three percentage points top to bottom quartile.
Leverage buyouts,
13.7 percent difference,
top quartile to bottom quartile.
And the venture capital,
43.2 percentage points difference,
top to bottom quartile.
So the measure that we have here
of market inefficiency points us
toward spending our time and energy
trying to find the best venture capital managers,
trying to find the best leverage buyout managers,
and spending far less of our time and energy
trying to beat the bond market
or beat the stock market,
because even if you win there,
and even if you end up in the top quartile,
you're not adding an enormous amount of value
relative to what you would have had
if you just would have bought the market.
So with that background,
let's revisit
the criticisms that Barron's leveled
at the Yale Model and the Swenson approach.
First of all, they talk about diversification failing.
And the fact is that in a panic,
only two things matter,
risk and safety.
And I saw this in 1987,
saw it in 1998 with the collapse of long-term capital,
and saw it in 2008,
and saw it in a
way that was even more profound
than in 87 and 98.
Investors sold everything
that had risk associated with it
to buy U.S. Treasuries.
Safety was all that mattered.
And of course,
in that narrow window of time,
diversification does fail.
The only diversification that would matter in that instance
is owning U.S. Treasuries.
But if you owned a
substantial amount of U.S. Treasury bonds,
and what's a substantial amount?
25, 30, 35% of your portfolio,
then under normal circumstances,
under the circumstances in which
we live most of our lives,
you're paying a huge opportunity cost.
So you could have a
portfolio with 30% in U.S. Treasuries,
and year in and year out,
you would pay this opportunity cost,
and then when the crisis comes,
you can be happy for
6 or 12 or 18 months,
and then you go back to paying the opportunity cost.
And I would argue that
if you expand your time horizon
to a sensible length of time,
that the strategy where you hold relatively little
in the high opportunity cost U.S. Treasuries
is the best strategy for a long-term investor.
And there are those who say that,
well, if diversification doesn't protect
you in times of crisis,
what does it matter?
Why would you want to diversify?
Well, think about Japan.
If you were a local Japanese investor,
you wanted to have an equity bias in your portfolio,
so you owned lots of Japanese stuff,
lots of Japanese stocks.
In 1989, at the end of the year,
the Nikkei closed at about 38,000.
At the end of 2009, 20 years later,
the Nikkei closed at 10,500.
So with your long time horizon
and equity bias in your portfolio over two decades,
you would have lost 73%.
So diversification makes an enormous amount of sense
in the long run,
even if there are occasional panics
where you're disappointed that the diversified approach
that you had to managing the portfolio
didn't produce results.
The second criticism, over-emphasis and alternatives,
let's just look at the last decade in Yale's portfolio.
Over the 10 years ended June 30, 2010,
domestic equities produced returns
of negative 0.7% per year.
Bonds produced returns of 5.9% per year.
Let's look at the alternatives
as opposed to domestic marketable securities.
Private equity, 6.2% per year.
Real estate, 6.9% per year.
Absolute return, 11.1% per year.
Timber, 12.1% per year.
And oil and gas, 24.7% per year.
I think the numbers speak
for themselves.
If you have a sensibly long time horizon,
these basic principles of equity orientation
and diversification make an enormous amount of sense.
And if you look at the bottom line,
which is performance,
when I began managing Yale's endowment in 1985,
it was less than a billion dollars,
the amount that we distributed
to support Yale's operations that year
was 45 million dollars.
For the year ended June 30, 2010,
the endowment stood at a
little bit above 16 billion dollars,
and the amount that we distributed
to Yale's operations was 1.1 billion dollars.
So an enormous change over,
enormous positive change over 25 years.
And if you look at Yale's performance
over the last 10 years,
it's still better than that
of any other institutional investor,
8.9% per annum.
And that compares to an average
for colleges and universities
of about 4.0% per annum.
And that translates into
7.9 billion dollars of added value
relative to where we would have been
had we had average returns over the past 10 years.
And the comparable numbers for 20 years are
Yale at 13.1% per annum,
again, the best record of any institutional investor
in the United States,
relative to an average for colleges and universities
of 8.8% per annum,
and 12.1 billion dollars of value added.
So,
the slings and arrows of outrageous fortune.
I would suggest that the Barron's articles
really took far too short a time horizon
in looking at
Yale's performance
and in looking at the
Yale model,
which emphasizes a portfolio
that's well diversified
and has a strong equity bias.
And I think if we were back in this room
five years or 10 years from now,
we'll see that the portfolio
will continue to produce
the same kind of strong long run results
as it has for the past 10 and 20 years.
With that, I'd love to
answer any questions that you might have.
Thank you.
How is your job similar or different
to a hedge fund manager would you?
And what are the concerns that an institutional investor
has to have versus a personal investor
as well, just like, well, being individual?
So, the fundamental difference between
what we would be doing at Yale
as opposed to a hedge fund manager
or a domestic stock,
or a manager,
or a buyout manager,
is that we're essentially one step
removed from the security selection process.
So our job is to
find the best hedge fund managers,
find the best domestic equity managers,
find the best buyout managers,
and put together
partnerships that work for them
and work for the university.
And it's a tricky thing
to do because in the funds management world
there are all sorts of issues
with respect to what economists call
the principal-agent problem.
And we're principals for the university
engaging agents,
the hedge fund managers
or the buyout managers,
in trying to find ways
to get those agents
to act primarily
in the university's interests,
to get rid of those agency issues.
And it's a challenge,
but a fascinating challenge
because in doing this
you end up meeting
an enormous number of incredibly
intelligent, engaged,
thoughtful individuals
that are involved in the funds management business.
And it's a fabulous career,
at least from my perspective,
because I get to do this
and do it to benefit
one of the world's great institutions,
Yale.
In terms of differences between
individuals and institutions,
there are some structural differences.
We don't pay taxes,
and taxes are an enormously important
determinant of investment outcomes
for individuals.
As an individual,
you want to avoid paying taxes
or defer paying taxes
because taxes are just a huge drag
on investment returns.
We don't have to worry about that,
by and large,
in managing Yale's portfolio.
Another very fundamental difference
has to do with the resources
that we can bring to
the investment management problem.
Most individuals,
and many institutions,
just don't have the
wherewithal,
either the background or the time,
to make high quality,
active management decisions.
Markets are incredibly tough.
Beating those markets
is an incredibly difficult challenge.
And doing it by spending
a couple hours on a weekend
once a month
isn't going to cut it.
So at Yale,
we've got 20, 21, 22
investment professionals
who are dedicating their careers
to trying to make these high quality
active management decisions.
And so we can go out
and have a decent shot
at beating the domestic stock market
and the foreign stock market
and putting together a superior
portfolio of venture capital
partnerships and
hedge fund managers.
And over the past 5, 10, 15, 20 years,
we've produced market beating results.
In contrast,
an individual has almost no chance
of beating the market.
So I've written two books,
one, Pioneering Portfolio Management,
that talks about how it is that
I think institutions should manage
their portfolio.
And if they've got the resources,
and it's not just dollars,
it's the huge amount
of human resources,
to make those high quality decisions,
they can follow what Barron's referred to
as the Yale model
or the Swenson approach.
But the book that I've written for,
ostensibly for individuals,
but it's really individuals
and institutions that don't have
the same resources that Yale does
to make these high quality
active decisions,
that book says basically
what you should do is
come up with a sensible
asset allocation policy
and then implement it using index funds,
which are low cost ways
of mimicking the market.
And oh, by the way,
because they have very low turnover,
generate very little in terms of
tax consequences for the holders
of those funds.
So it's kind of an interesting world
where the right solution,
I think,
is to have a system
that's either at one extreme
or the other extreme.
You're either completely passive
or you're aggressively active.
But as in most things,
most people are kind of in the middle,
right?
They're neither aggressively active
nor completely passive.
But in the middle, you lose
because you end up paying high fees
for mediocre active results.
And that's where most people end up
in most institutions.
嗯
So my question is about, given you were talking about
your equity orientation advice,
and given what's going on
right now with the stock market,
just what your views are,
whether or not the stock market is currently expensive,
and whether or not you
have any money in tech stocks
with all the valuations and that sales
that have been going on in that space.
What do you think about that,
and also what would you do in terms of investing
in response to what your view is?
So one of the great things about having
a diversified portfolio is that you can worry less
about the relative level of valuation
of the various assets in which you invest.
So if you go back to the mid-80s,
and you've got a portfolio that's 50% in domestic stocks,
you have to worry a lot about the valuation
of that portfolio, because half of your assets
are in that single asset class.
But if you've got a well-diversified portfolio
with, let's say, minimum allocation of 5 to 10%,
and a maximum allocation of 25 to 30%
in an individual asset class,
the relative valuation of each of those asset classes
matters less.
And there's another kind of nice aspect
to a rebalancing policy.
If you're investing in a stock,
it's going to be the same thing.
If you set up your targets
and you faithfully adhere to those
targets, suppose that domestic equities have poor relative
performance.
Well, then you're going to
buy domestic equities to get them
back up to target, selling whatever it is that had
superior relative performance to fund those purchases, and
vice versa.
If domestic equities have great relative performance,
you'll be selling to get back to your long-term target
and buying other assets that have shown
poor relative performance.
So if you're in a circumstance where domestic stocks are
expensive, where you're selling into this superior relative
performance that the domestic equities are exhibiting,
thereby maintaining your risk exposure at a level that's
consistent with what's implicit
in your policy asset allocation.
So that's kind of a long way
of saying that if somebody asked me
whether stocks are expensive or
cheap, my first line of defense,
it doesn't really matter all that
much to me because we're well
diversified and because we do a great job of rebalancing.
But the reality is that those
questions are just incredibly tough to
answer.
if they were easier to answer, I guess I'd be much
more excited about market timing as a way to generate returns.
In terms of the second question with respect to technology,
Yale's had a longstanding commitment to venture capital.
And over the decades, it's
produced extraordinary returns for the university.
And we continue to have
a world-class group of venture capitalists.
We've got exposure to companies
like LinkedIn and Facebook and Groupon.
And I hope that this wave of IPOs that
people are writing about in the press actually occurs
because that would be very
good for the university's portfolio.
It's been a long time.
We benefited enormously.
We've been in the internet bubble in the late 90s.
And the last decade's been a bit fallow.
We also find on the marketable security side that technology
stocks tend to be less efficiently priced than many other securities.
And so we have a manager that
is heavily focused on information technology stocks
and another manager that's very
heavily focused on biotechnology stocks.
And both those managers.
They've produced very handsome
absolute and relative returns.
And that's an important part
of our domestic equity strategy.
Thank you, John.
I just have a quick question.
So the reason you used the number of
hedge funds, private equity first, as a spot.
And I wasn't sure how that's changed.
I mean, there are a lot
of hedge funds that are very efficient.
But the question is, the efficiencies
of the alternative asset allocation markets.
And it has changed the efficiencies.
How do you change your investment prospects?
And I was wondering also, what are the structural patterns of
these markets that would prevent the market from becoming very efficient,
even if there are a lot of
hedge funds and a lot of .
So that's a really good question.
I think the most important thing
is that the market becomes very efficient.
And I think the most fundamental issue with the explosion
of hedge funds and the explosion of private equity funds
has to do with this negative
sum game that we were talking about.
If you go back to the 1950s, the
most common way that institutional assets were managed
would be for an institution like Yale to go
to a bank like Chemical Bank or J.P. Morgan.
And they would pay a small fraction
of 1% of the cost of a company.
And again, that was a very small amount,
So you can reduce this to 30%
for a reasonably diversified portfolio of stocks, bonds
and it would probably be some
foreign stocks and some domestic stocks,
but the leakage from the system was very small.
And you look at hedge funds and private equity funds,
they are essentially dealing with the same set of securities
that an institution used to pay
2 tenths of a percent a year
or three tenths of a percent of a year
they were going through and they
would pay a little bit less.
for admittedly sleepy bank management.
But it's the same set of securities.
Now those securities are traded in a hedge fund format
or taken private in a private equity fund format.
And the fees that you're paying are a point,
a point and a half, two points,
right, the typical two and 20.
And you're paying a significant percentage of the profits,
the 20 and the two and 20.
Think about that.
The leakage from the system that goes to Wall Street
is enormous compared to what it was 10 years ago
or 20 years ago or 30 years ago.
So there's that much less left for us as investors.
And I think that that has huge,
huge consequences for endowments, foundations,
pension plans, institutions of all stripes
and to the extent that individuals get exposure
to these types of assets
and they're largely wealthy individuals
that end up getting the exposure,
they're gonna suffer the same consequences
of this huge leakage of higher fees
and the profits interest to Wall Street.
The question as to whether or not the money flowing
to hedge funds is gonna make markets more efficient
and take away opportunities,
I don't worry too much about that.
I mean, I think that the
best talent is going to hedge funds
because if they're in a long only domestic equity
environment, maybe they can charge
three quarters of a percent
or a percent or if
they're in the mutual fund world,
maybe they charge a percent and a half
or something like that.
Well, you'd rather have two and 20 than 0.75, right?
That's easy.
So there's a huge migration of talent
to the hedge fund world.
But what I care about
when I look at the degree
of investment opportunities is this dispersion
that we talked about and I haven't seen the dispersion
of results, top quartile, the bottom quartile,
compress it all.
So I don't think that we're increasing the efficiency
of the pricing of assets.
I still need to go out
there and be able to identify people
in the top quartile or top
decile so that we can win relative
to the markets after adjustment
for the risks that we take.
So as long as we have
plenty of dispersion in the results,
it's still an interesting activity for us to pursue.
I think we have one more question.
Okay.
It better be good.
That's the last question.
Okay.
So my question is about
the performance of the other studio
and we heard that it grew from
1 billion to less than 1 billion
In 1989 to 16 billion, which is very impressive.
And it's not going to use the .
It's not going to be the same.
It's going to be the same thing.
It's going to be the same
thing for the next 20 years.
What are your thoughts on the fact that the .
But what about the ratio?
And why do you think
that people talk more about total
So I think that one of
the things that needs to happen
in the funds management world
is that we need to have
better measures of risk.
And so one of the
reasons why I don't talk about
the Sharpe ratio is that just looking at
standard deviation of returns doesn't capture risk
in a way that is meaningful.
I mean, I've seen other people do an analysis
of the Yale portfolio and show relative Sharpe ratios,
and obviously because our returns have been so good,
and if you just look
at the pattern of those returns,
we end up scoring high when looking at Sharpe ratios
across different institutional portfolios.
But the risks that exist in a Yale portfolio
and the portfolio aren't really captured
by standard deviation of the returns.
Just a quick example, if you
look at real estate or timber
or even any of our illiquid assets,
they're appraised relatively infrequently.
There tends to be a huge stability basis, right,
a bias in the appraisals.
If somebody looks at a piece of real estate
12 months ago, six months ago, and today,
they're likely to see pretty much the same thing
that they saw over that period.
You compare and contrast that to the volatility
that you've got in the stock market.
I think Bob Shiller deserves credit for the,
coining the term excess volatility.
There's no question that stock prices
are way more variable than they need to be to
adjust for changes in the underlying fundamentals.
So if you've got a portfolio
that's largely marketable securities,
you're gonna see a lot more standard deviation of returns
than if you've got one of illiquid assets
where you've got this kind of stability built in
because of the appraisal nature of the valuation process.
And if you end up, you know,
comparing those two portfolios,
one dominated by marketable securities,
one dominated by Josh Moore.
This would help if a few states
in should decide to buy me then
by private assets, you're going to end
up with measures that are apples and oranges.
So with that, thank you very much.